Guide to the Tamiment Library Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.) Web Collection TAM.507
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
- Labor Unions and Organizations (U.S.), 2007-present
  - Social Service Employees Union Local 371, Sep 2007-present
    Founded in 1965, Social Service Employees Union Local 371 is part of District Council 37 of the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees AFL-CIO (AFSCME), which represents workers employed by New York City in social service professions.
  - Southwest Workers Union, Jul 2012-present
    Southwest Workers Union, launched in May of 1988 in Hondo, Texas, is an organization of low-income workers and families, community residents, and youth, united in the struggle for worker rights, environmental justice and community empowerment. The union organizes 2500 members. The website contains resources and news.
  - Starbucks Workers Union (IWW), Sep 2007-present
    The Starbucks Workers Union is an organization of employees at Starbucks (a coffee chain) united for a living wage, secure work hours, and respect on the job. They are affiliated with the Industrial Workers of the World.
  - Stella Doro Strike 2008, Aug 2009-May 2011
    On August 13, 2008, over 135 members of Bakery, Confectionery, Tobacco Workers and Grain Millers International Union Local 50, employed at the Stella D'Oro plant in the Bronx, went on strike citing proposed pay and benefit cuts, and later picketed the company's attempt to bring in replacement workers.In early September 2010, a 2 to 1 ruling by the National Labor Relations Board affirmed the June 2009 decision of an administrative law judge that Stella D'oro violated federal labor law by refusing to furnish detailed financial statements to the workers' union to support claims of needing contract concessions to survive. The factory closed in October 2009. This website was a support page for the strike which posted news and other information.
  - Street Vendors Mobilizing and Organizing in Solidarity, May 2012-present
    Vendedoras Ambulantes Movilizando y Organizando en Solidaridad (VAMOS Unidos or Street Vendors Mobilizing and Organizing in Solidarity) is a Bronx based social justice organization, founded in 2007 by low income Latino/Latina street vendors. The organization works to organize Latino immigrants, for economic and racial justice, immigrant rights, and police accountability. The website contains information on provided services, news, photos, and videos.
  - Teamsters for a Democratic Union, Feb 2007-present
    Teamsters for a Democratic Union, founded in 1976, is a rank-and-file union democracy movement organizing to reform the International Brotherhood of Teamsters (IBT). TDU was created out of the merger of the Professional Drivers Council (PROD) and TDU in 1979. They represent truck drivers, dock workers, warehouse workers, and clericals.
  - The WAGE Project, Nov 2009-present
    The WAGE Project (Women Are Getting Even) is an organization that was established to end discrimination against women in the American workplace. The project offers resources and workshops to help close the wage gap. WAGE is led by Evelyn F. Murphy, author of Getting Even: Why Women Don't Get Paid Like Men and What To Do About It. Dr. Murphy is a Ph.D. economist, former Lt. Governor of Massachusetts; and by Annie Houle, National Director of Campus and Community Initiatives.
  - Transport Workers Union of America, Sep 2007-present
    The Transport Workers Union of America (TWU) is a labor union that was founded in 1934 by subway workers in New York City. Today, the TWU has four divisions: Railroad; Gaming; Airline; Transit; and Utility, University and Service. The Union has 114 autonomous locals representing over 200,000 members and retirees in 22 states around the country. The TWU is a member of the AFL-CIO and the International Transport Workers Federation (ITF).
  - Transport Workers Union of America, Local 100, Sep 2007-present
    Local 100 is a local of the Transport Workers Union of America. The Local primarily represents workers in the New York City public transportation system and at some private bus lines serving the New York City metropolitan area.
  - UFT Alliance of Charter Teachers and Staff, Nov 2011-present
    The United Federation of Teachers Alliance of Charter Teachers and Staff (UFT ACTS ) is a community of charter school employees organized by the UFT, which is a local union chapter of the American Federation of Teachers (AFT) and represents public school teachers, some private school teachers and other professionals in New York City. The UFT is affiliated with the statewide New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) and the national American Federation of Teachers (AFT). The UFT represents 13 charter schools in New York City.
  - Union Communications Services, Dec 2012-present
    Union Communication Services, Inc. was founded in 1981 by David Prosten, a former publications and public relations director and staffer for several national unions. The website publishes and distributes steward advice, labor news, graphics and books that help progressive union leaders rally their members and build their unions. The organization is used by over 2000 unions in the United States and Canada. The website also contains a listing of every union website.
  - Union Democracy Review, Feb 2007-present
    The Union Democracy Review is the bi-monthly publication of the Association for Union Democracy.
  - Union Jobs Clearinghouse, Sep 2007-present
    Union Jobs Clearinghouse, is a site for posting the open staffing and trades positions in unions and allied organizations in the U.S. and throughout the world that are currently accepting applications.
  - Union Label, May 2012-present
    The Union Label and Service Trades Department, AFL-CIO, was founded in 1909 to promote the products and services produced in America by union members, specifically products and services identified by a union label, shop card, store card and service button. The website contains information on current boycotts, personal stories, news, a photo gallery, and their publication, the Label Letter.
  - Union of Clerical, Administrative and Technical Staff at NYU, Local 3882, NYSUT, AFT, AFL-CIO, Sep 2007-present
    Union of Clerical, Administrative & Technical Staff, Local 3882, NYSUT, AFT, AFL-CIO (UCATS), founded in 1978, is a labor union that represents over 1500 clerical, administrative, and technical staff at New York University. They are affiliated with the American Federation of Teachers and were formerly known as the United Staff Association of NYU.
  - Union Songs, Aug 2009-present
    Union Songs is an online collection of lyrics, discography, bibliography, and filmography of songs related to the labor movement. The website contains links to union music and other cultural sites. The coverage is international, but the coverage of Australia is extensive. The website contains over 770 songs and poems and over 300 authors.
  - UnionBook, Jul 2009-present
    UnionBook is a social networking website for trade unionists and a project of LabourStart. The website has a microblogging feature called the Wire.
  - Unite Here (Organization), Sep 2007-present
    UNITE HERE is the merger of two labor unions, the Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE) and the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees International Union (HERE). UNITE HERE, founded in 2004, is a labor union in the United States and Canada with more than 265,000 active members. The union's members work predominantly in the hotel, food service, laundry, warehouse, and casino gaming industries. It is currently affiliated with the AFL-CIO.
  - United American Nurses (UAN), Dec 2009-Sep 2011
    United American Nurses (UAN) was an American union affiliated with the AFL-CIO. Founded in 1999 and dissolved in 2009, it represented registered nurses (RNs). In 2009, UAN merged with the California Nurses Association/National Nurses Organizing Committee and Massachusetts Nurses Association to form National Nurses United.
  - United Association for Labor Education, Aug 2009-present
    The United Association for Labor Education (UALE), created out of a merger between the Workers’ Education Local 189 and the University and College Labor Education Association in 2000, is an international association for post-secondary, community, union and associated labor educators. The UALE co-publishes the Labor Studies Journal with West Virginia University.
  - United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and Pipe Fitting Industry of the United States and Canada (UA), Jan 2010-present
    Founded in 1889, the United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing, Pipefitting and Sprinkler Fitting Industry of the United States and Canada, (United Association, UA) is a trade union of journeymen and apprentices of the plumbing, pipefitting, and sprinkler fitting industry of the United States and Canada. The members fabricate, install, and service piping systems. There are approximately 340,000 highly-skilled United Association members who belong to over 300 individual local unions across North America.
  - United Brotherhood of Carpenters, Apr 2012-present
    United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America (UBC), founded in 1881, is a building trade union with approximately a half-million members in the construction and wood-products industries. UBC members consist of carpenters, millwrights, interior systems and framing and residential carpenters, floor coverers, pile drivers, lathers, and millworkers and cabinetmakers. The website contains information on training programs, partnership programs, and legislative issues.
  - United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Cabinetmakers Local 2090, Mar 2009-present
    The United Brotherhood of Carpenters Shop and Industrial Local 2790 was formed in August 2011, from the dissolution of the Architectural Woodworkers Local 2090 and Industrial Local 2870. UBC Local Union 2790 is a specialty trade union that represents carpenters, industrial shop workers, architectural woodworkers, millworkers, finish carpenters, wood finishers, cabinet installers, trim carpenters, architectural metal workers, and cabinetmakers throughout the five boroughs of New York City; as well as Long Island, New Jersey, and Westchester County. Local 2790 is part of the United Brotherhood of Carpenters & Joiners of America, and the New York City District Council of Carpenters.
  - United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE), May 2012-present
    United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America or the Rank-and-File Union (UE) is a national union representing some 35,000 workers in a wide variety of manufacturing, public sector and private non-profit sector jobs. UE is an independent union (not affiliated with the AFL-CIO). Members work in electrical manufacturing, metalworking and plastics as plastic injection molders, tool and die makers, sheet metal workers, truck drivers, warehouse workers, and custodians. The website contains a blog, information for workers and unions, and political action campaigns.
  - United Farm Workers of America, Dec 2009-present
    Founded in 1962 by Cesar Chavez, the United Farm Workers of America represents farm workers in the United States. Formed from the merger of the Agricultural Workers Organizing Committee and the National Farm Workers Association, it is affiliated with the Change to Win Federation.
  - United Federation of Teachers, Sep 2007-present
    The United Federation of Teachers (Local 2 of the American Federation of Teachers) represents more than 200,000 people, and is the sole bargaining agent for most of the non-supervisory educators who work in the New York City public schools. It represents approximately 74,000 teachers and 17,000 classroom paraprofessionals, along with school secretaries, attendance teachers, guidance counselors, psychologists, social workers, education evaluators, nurses, laboratory technicians, adult education teachers and 32,000 retired members. The UFT also represents teachers and other employees of some private educational institutions. The allied Federation of Nurses/UFT represents some 2,500 registered nurses of the New York City Visiting Nurse Service and several private New York City hospitals and health care institutions. The union led a successful organizing drive to gain collective-bargaining rights for 28,000 New York City home child-care providers in 2007.
  - United Food and Commercial Workers International Union (UFCW), Dec 2009-present
    The United Food and Commercial Workers International Union, founded in 1979, is a labor union representing approximately 1.3 million workers in the United States and Canada in many industries, including agriculture, health care, meatpacking, poultry and food processing, manufacturing, textile, chemical trades, and retail food. It is affiliated with the Change to Win Coalition.
  - United Mine Workers of America (UMWA), Dec 2009-present
    Founded in 1890, The United Mine Workers of America is a North American labor union which has represented coal miners and coal technicians. Today, the Union also represents health care workers, truck drivers, manufacturing workers and public employees in the United States and Canada.
  - United Scenic Artists, Local 829, Jun 2013-present
    United Scenic Artists [founded in 1897 as the United Scenic Artists Association], Local USA 829, is a labor union and professional association of Designers, Artists and Craftspeople organized to protect craft standards, working conditions and wages for the entertainment and decorative arts industries. The members of Local USA 829 are Artists and Designers working in film, theatre, opera, ballet, television, industrial shows, commercials and exhibitions.
  - United Steel, Paper and Forestry, Rubber, Manufacturing, Energy, Allied Industrial and Service Workers International Union (USW), Dec 2009-present
    The United Steel, Paper and Forestry, Rubber, Manufacturing, Energy, Allied Industrial and Service Workers International Union (United Steelworkers or USW), founded in 1942, is the largest industrial labor union in North America, with 705,000 members. Headquartered in Pittsburgh, U.S., the United Steelworkers represents workers in the United States, Canada and the Caribbean. The United Steelworkers represent workers in a diverse range of industries, including primary and fabricated metals, chemicals, glass, rubber, heavy-duty conveyor belting, tires, transportation, utilities, container industries, pharmaceuticals, call centers and health care.
  - United Transportation Union (UTU), Dec 2009-present
    The United Transportation Union (UTU), founded in 1969, is a transportation labor union representing about 125,000 active and retired railroad, bus, mass transit, and airline workers in the United States with more than 600 locals. It is headquartered in Cleveland, OH and affiliated with the AFL-CIO.
  - United Union of Roofers, Waterproofers and Allied Workers (Roofers and Waterproofers), Dec 2009-present
    The United Union of Roofers, Waterproofers and Allied Workers, founded in 1903, has approximately 22,000 members organized into nine district councils across the United States. Members participate in the National Roofing Industry Supplemental Pension, Multi-trade Organizing Volunteer Education program (MOVE), health and safety programs, as well as training and apprenticeship opportunities, and cooperative labor-management research and education efforts.
  - United Workers, May 2011-present
    The United Workers, founded in 2002 by homeless day laborers in Baltimore, is a human rights organization led by low-wage workers. They fight for fair development, which respects human rights, maximizes public benefits, and is sustainable. The organization focuses on understanding the root causes of poverty and organizing around universal human rights. They work for change through conferences and campaigns, including The Living Wages at Camden Yards Campaign.
  - UPPNET, Aug 2009-present
    The Union Producers and Programmers Network Online (UPPNET) provided links to television and radio programs for organized labor and working people, campaigned to make labor media a priority within the labor movement, and published the online UPPNET Newsletter. The site has been inactive since 2007.
  - US Federation of Worker Cooperatives, Nov 2011-present
    The United States Federation of Worker Cooperatives, founded in 2004, is a national grassroots membership organization of and for worker cooperatives, democratic workplaces, and organizations that support the growth and development of worker cooperatives. The organization offers resources and education for worker cooperatives.
  - US Labor Against the War, Sep 2007-present
    U.S. Labor Against the War, was founded in 2003 in opposition to the Iraq War, Its principles include: to advocate, educate and mobilize in the US labor movement for: a just foreign policy that will bring genuine security and prosperity to working people and an end to U.S. occupation of foreign countries, replaced by the reconstruction of war-devastated nations with the full support of the international community and the full participation and decision-making power of affected peoples. The organization also supports the broader social justice ideals associated with the labor movement.
  - Utility Workers Union of America, Local 1-2, Feb 2009-present
    Local 1-2 of the Utility Workers Union of America evolved out of the Utility Workers Organizing Committee (UWOC) established by the Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) in 1938. In 1946, with more than 180 locals organized nationwide, the UWOC transformed itself into the Utility Workers Union of America, CIO. Local 1-2 represents New York area with members working in the electric, gas, water, and nuclear industries across the United States.
  - Utility Workers Union of America (UWUA), Dec 2009-present
    The Utility Workers Union of America, AFL-CIO (UWUA), is a union with over 50,000 members working in the electric, gas, water, and nuclear industries across the United States. It represents utility workers in municipal, as well as publicly traded utilities. Fields include power generation (power plants), power distribution (transmission and distribution), call/service center employees, as well as natural gas and water utilities.
  - Vermont Workers' Center, May 2011-present
    Vermont Workers’ Center was founded in 1996 by a group of low-income workers in Central Vermont. The Vermont Workers' Center is a democratic, member-run organization dedicated to organizing for workers' rights and living wages for all Vermonters. They organize rallies, public hearings, forums, publicizing peoples' stories, and taking direct action, we support workers throughout the state who are trying to improve their wages, benefits, rights on the job, working conditions and their communities. It is affiliated with Jobs for Justice and Grassroots Global Justice.
  - Wobbly City: Newsletter of the NYC Branch (IWW), Jul 2009-present
    Wobbly City is the official blog of the New York City General Membership Branch (GMB) of the Industrial Workers of the World (IWW).
  - Women on the Job, Mar 2009-present
    Women on the Job (WOJ) was founded in 1981 as a private, not-for-profit advocacy organization dedicated to achieving women’s equality in the workplace on Long Island. WOJ was a project of Resources for Program Development, Inc. (RPD), which had been established with funding from the North Shore Unitarian Universalist Society VEATCH Program. The WOJ program was initiated in October 1981 by co-founders Lillian McCormick and Charlotte Shapiro. Its mission was to foster equal employment opportunities for women and combat workplace discrimination against women in Long Island communities.
  - Workers Stand for America, Aug 2012-present
    Worker’s Stand for America is the website of a national worker’s rally that took place August 11, 2012 in Philadelphia. The rally worked to change the political focus toward job creation, worker’s rights, and education reform. The website contains a video of the entire rally, news and press releases, and their Second Bill of Rights, which is a petition that calls for the right to full employment and a living wage; the right to full participation in the electoral process; right to a voice at work, the right to quality education; and the right to a secure, healthy future.
  - Working America, Oct 2011-present
    Working America, founded in 2003, is an allied organization of the AFL-CIO which works to build alliances among non-union working people. Working America is a nonpartisan, non-profit organization which provides workers who are not union members input into the policies, goals, and legislative efforts of the AFL-CIO. It also recruits people to help with letter-writing campaigns, canvassing, and other activities to promote causes important to the labor federation.
  - Working-Class Perspectives, Jan 2010-present
    Working-Class Perspectives (founded July, 2008) is the blog of the Center for Working-Class Studies at Youngstown State University (Ohio). Working-Class Perspectives offers weekly commentaries on current issues related to working-class people and communities. Contributors discuss a variety of issues, from what class means to how it intersects with race and gender to how class is shaping American politics.
  - Working Life, Sep 2007-present
    WorkingLife.org is the blog of the Labor Research Association (LRA), which was founded in 1927 to collect data on labor for trade unions and publish that information, statistics, and related news, and was for many years informally associated with the Communist Party USA. The Labor Research Association is a New York City-based non-profit research and advocacy organization that provides research and educational services for trade unions. LRA's work is overseen by a Board of Directors composed of union leaders and others involved in the labor movement. The website fosters discussion on work, the economy, and labor.
  - Writers Guild of America, East Inc. (WGAE), Dec 2009-present
    The Writers Guild of America, East, founded in 1951, is a labor union of thousands of professionals who are the primary creators of what is seen or heard on television and film in the U.S., as well as digital media content. The Guild negotiates contracts, make sure on-screen credits are fair and accurate, and provides education and training for members. The Writers Guild of America, East is affiliated with the Writers Guild of America, West. Together the guilds administer the Writers Guild of America Awards. It is an affiliate of both the International Federation of Journalists and the International Affiliation of Writers Guilds, as well as an affiliate of the AFL-CIO.